A Guide to the Stanislaw Makielski Architectural Drawings, 1928-1968, n.d.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Stanislaw Makielski Architectural Drawings 1928-1968, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10768
This collection consists of 409 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These drawings were given to the Library by Ms. Jane Dandridge of Charlottesville, Virginia, on June 30, 1988.
Biographical/ Historical Information
Makielski, a member of the American Institute of Architects, was born in South Bend Indiana, in 1893 to Polish immigrants, Alexander and Elizabeth (Nadolni) Makielski. He attended Notre Dame for two and a half years but received his degree in architecture in 1922 from the University of Virginia. He served in the Aviation Service during World War I and became the first instructor in the new School of Architecture at the University of Virginia under Fiske Kimball in 1919, where he remained on the faculty until 1955. [This biographical information was taken from a biographical sketch by K. Edward Lay, October 1988, in the control folder.]
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains the architectural drawings of Charlottesville architect and member of the architecture faculty at the University of Virginia, Stanislaw John Makielski (1893-1969), and consists of 409 items, 1928-1968, and undated. These include drawings of central Virginia residences, churches, and businesses; University of Virginia buildings and renovations, such as the Bayly Art Museum (including the drawings by Edmund S. Campbell, 1933), the Cafeteria, Minor Hall, the Electrical Engineering Laboratories, and the Medical Records Storage Center; and normal schools in the South, including the St. Paul Normal & Industrial School, Lawrenceville, Virginia, and the Voorhees Normal & Industrial School, Denmark, South Carolina.
Other material found in the control folder includes: a letter from the Chief Fire Marshal concerning the Pantops Restaurant (1956 Feb 28); notes re Carter's Gun Works (1964); plot diagram of a lot belonging to Paul S. Coiner, Harold P. Johnson, and Lionel S. Key, Charlottesville (1949); specifications concerning the refectory building at St. Paul Normal & Industrial School, Lawrenceville, Virginia (1941); and a newsclipping re the new Greenwood Post Office [1965 ?].
Contents List
- Maps of Charlottesville 1955, One map hand-drawn in pencil and one printed (Folder 1)
- Mayo, W.M., Jr.- Plat for a Subdivision in Albemarle County 1957 (Folder 1)
- Six Hundred Delaware Avenue Proposed Layout by Calvin P. Hamilton n.d., 3 sheets (Folder 1)
- Town & Country Motor Lodge 1955, Pen and ink drawing (Folder 1)
- Unidentified Apartment or Office Building n.d. (Folder 1)
- Watercolors of two unidentified buildings n.d. (Folder 1)
- Cardinal Motor Court, Albemarle County 1955-1958, 13 sheets (Folder 2)
- Hot Shop Restaurant Addition, Rt. 29 North, Albemarle County 1955, 2 sheets (Folder 2)
- Unidentified interior perspectives of a racquetball or squash courts n.d., 3 sheets (Folder 2)
- Unidentified perspective renderings and exterior elevations of modern apartments n.d., 4 sheets (Folder 2)
- Carter's Gun Works Additions, Charlottesville 1959-1964 (Folder 3)
- Georgetown Veterinary Hospital for Dr. Daniel V. Flynn, Albemarle County 1961-1965, 14 sheets (Folder 3)
- Lucky "7" Store & Restaurant, Cherry Avenue, Charlottesville 1965 (Folder 3)
- Mayo, W.M. - Additions to Garden Apartment & Carport, Albemarle County 1958-1959, 3 sheets (Folder 3)
- Church of the Holy Rosary, Richmond, Virginia 1962-1966, 15 sheets (Folder 4)
- Town & Country Motor Lodge Restaurant, Albemarle County 1955-1956, 26 sheets (Folder 4)
- Bishop Payne Divinity School, Petersburg, Virginia 1941, 18 sheets (Folder 5)
- Blue Run Farm, Somerset, Virginia, Residence of Col. W. Whitaker 1944, 2 sheets (Folder 5)
- Eastern Sales, Don King n.d. (Folder 5)
- Greenwood Post Office Alterations, Greenwood, Virginia 1965, 3 sheets (Folder 5)
- Gymnasium Swimming Pool Study n.d., 8 sheets (Folder 5)
- Mayo, W.M. - Commercial Building, Albemarle County 1965, 13 sheets (Folder 5)
- St. Paul Normal & Industrial School, Lawrenceville, Virginia 1932-1935, 43 sheets (Folder 6)
- Unidentified Office Interiors n.d., 4 sheets (Folder 6)
- Bayly Art Museum, University of Virginia 1933, 14 sheets (Folder 7)
  By Edmund S. Campbell & R.E. Lee Taylor, Architects
- Bayly Art Museum Additions, University of Virginia 1964, 16 sheets (Folder 7)
- Cafeteria, University of Virginia 1943, 2 sheets (Folder 8)
- Minor Hall, University of Virginia, Basement, Auditorium, Air Conditioning, & Roof 1955-1956, 11 sheets (Folder 8)
- Minor Hall, University of Virginia, Bureau of Public Administration Proposed Alterations 1960-1962, 13 sheets (Folder 8)
- Voorhees Normal & Industrial School, Denmark, South Carolina 1930-1935, 40 sheets (Folder 9)
  Includes Girl's Trade Building, Chapel, Kenwood Cottage, Practice Cottage, Teacher's Cottage, Girl's Dormitory, Boy's Dormitory.
- Voorhees Normal & Industrial School, Denmark, South Carolina 1930-1932, 1945, 27 sheets (Folder 10)
  Includes Plot Plan, Classroom Building (Massachusetts Building).
- Bisell, Harry B., Jr. - Residence, Greenville, Delaware 1966, 4 sheets (Folder 11)
  Drawings by Richard P. Fox, AIA, Newark, Delaware.
- Elkton Pedestrian Mall n.d., 6 sheets (Folder 11)
- "Hollihen Hall" Watercolor Drawing n.d. (Folder 11)
- Longwood Gardens, Kennett Square, Pennsylvania, Entrance Pavilion for the Azalea House 1968, 11 sheets (Folder 11)
- Physical Research Laboratory Experimental Station, E.I. Dupont Denemours & Company Engineering Department 1966 (Folder 11)
- Unidentified Apartment Building n.d., 2 sheets (Folder 11)
- Hanley, R.E., Grid Elevations for "Wilton," Charlottesville 1955, 2 sheets (Folder 12)
- Meadow Creek Motor Court, Route 29 North, Albemarle County 1953 (Folder 12)
- Preston Court Apartments, Charlottesville 1928, 34 sheets (Folder 12)
- Electrical Engineering Laboratories, University of Virginia 1968, 19 sheets (Folder 13)
- Medical Center Records Storage Center, University of Virginia 1956 (Folder 13)
- Unidentified Land Plot of a Normal & Industrial School 1928 (Folder 13)
- Unidentified Interior Perspectives of a Gym n.d., 4 sheets (Folder 13)
- Bissell, Harry B., Jr. - Residence, Greenville, Delaware 1966 (Folder 13)
  Drawings by Richard Philliips Fox.
- "Hollihen Hall" Colored Pencil Rendering n.d., 2 sheets (Folder 13)
  Drawings by Richard Phillips Fox.
- Ocean City, Maryland, Feasibility Study for Proposed Condominium 1968, 5 sheets (Folder 13)